### **Deven Patel**

deven.patel2@gmail.com +919819482499

#### **PROFILE**

A Computer Vision post graduate with experience as a developer as well as a researcher in the field of Image Processing and Computer Vision. Proficient with OpenCV on Linux as well as Android platforms and have extensively worked on relevant projects.

#### **EXPERIENCE**

### **Image Processing Consultant**

Binaryveda Software Ltd.

2014-Present

CBD-Belapur, Navi Mumbai.

- Developed an image matching and recognition feature for a photo-printer Android app. An 85% recognition accuracy was achieved. The application uses algorithms from computer vision as well as machine learning to extract features from the photograph using mobile camera and search a match from an existing database. The program uses techniques like SIFT-like feature matching, SVM, and other various computer vision methodologies.
- Developed a python based basic image analysis application. The application segments natural images into different components. It also does face detection, pedestrian detection and segmentation of images into super-pixels.
- Designed and developed an app feature that scans and recognizes simple logos using OCR and machine learning techniques. The app also performs pre-processing processing tasks like segmentation, circle detection etc.

# Assistant Professor RGIT.

2012- 2014

Andheri, Mumbai.

- Worked on two image processing based projects: Gesture Recognition, Head Tracking. The Gesture Recognition uses ideas from PCA based eigenfaces used for face recognition. The Head Tracking project used Viola-Jones face detector. The output of the face detector is then used to change the viewing angle of a simple augmented cube on the screen.
- Conducted courses and designed lab experiments/assignments for courses like DSP, Image Processing and Random Signal Analysis. These experiments included simulation of random processes, implementation of image processing algorithms like filtering, image transforms etc.
- Introduced the use of OpenCV for Image Processing laboratory. Prior to this Matlab was used for image processing laboratory. I promoted and introduced OpenCV for image processing experiments as it is more used in actual applications.

# Research Scholar IIT-B

2008-2012

Powai, Mumbai.

- Multiple low resolution images of the same scene are fused to super-resolve or obtain high resolution image of the scene. This technique is called Super-Resolution. The method outperforms simple interpolation techniques in terms of artifact removal, noise and PSNR. It gives higher quality high resolution image which are better than the popular bi-cubic or other interpolation techniques.
- This method is also then used for converting SDTV video to HDTV video. Frames in SDTV images are of lower resolution and a different aspect ratio than HDTV videos. Super-resolution was used for this conversion and the results were found to be better than simple resizing or interpolation.
- Used optical-flow for the SR-technique to free the process from the traditional global motion assumption. This enabled to do a point based-registration and discard a global translation/motion assumption. The method allows to register images that does not follow the global motion model.

### **EDUCATION**

Research Scholar, IIT-B, Mumbai.

M.Tech (ICT) from DA-IICT, Gandhinagar.

B.E (E.C) Saurashtra University, Gujarat.

## TECHNICAL SKILLS

Programming: C/C++, Python, Java, Linux Scripting
Tools: Matlab, Octave, OpenCV, Eclipse/Android Studio

## **PUBLICATION**

Deven Patel, Subhasis Chaudhuri: Performance Analysis for Image Super-Resolution Using Blur as a Cue. IEEE-ICAPR 2009